Guide to the Natalie W. Uhl papers, [ca. 1940-2005]
Uhl, Natalie W. papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Natalie W. Uhl papers, [ca. 1940-2005]
14-28-3883
Natalie W. Uhl
7 cubic feet.
Correspondence, Manuscripts, Printed Materials, Publications, Research Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Files relating to her research, writing, teaching, and other professional activities.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Natalie Whitford Uhl was born in 1919 and educated at Rhode Island State College and at Cornell University, where she worked with Arthur J. Eames. She received an M.S. in 1943 and a Ph.D in 1947 with a dissertation on the floral morphology and anatomy of the Helobiae. In 1963, she began working as a Research Associate for Harold E. Moore at the Bailey Hortorium at Cornell. They published numerous papers on palm anatomy and morphology. After Moore's death in 1980, Uhl continued their work on Genera Palmarum, a comprehensive review of the taxonomy, morphology and anatomy of all genera of palms, with the collaboration of John Dransfield. The work was finally published in 1987. Uhl formally retired in 1987, but maintained her activities in instruction, graduate student supervision, curation, and research. She undertook the first family-level cladistic analysis of the palms, the first study to use molecular data to study higher-level relationships in the palms. She also co-edited the journal Principes (now Palms) from 1979 to 2000. In 1981, she was appointed as Associate Professor at Cornell and taught Applied Plant Anatomy for many years. In 2002, she was awarded the Asa Gray Award byt the American Society of Plant Taxonomists in recognition of her outstanding accomplishments.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Files relating to her research, writing, teaching, and other professional activities. Class notes, labs, and other information from courses within Cornell University's plant biology department; seminar and conference outlines; various plant books and articles; research proposals, abstracts, and additional files of information centered on palm research; correspondence and travel notes regarding professional activities and research.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Uhl, Natalie W.; Liberty Hyde Bailey Hortorium.; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences.
Subjects:
Palms--Classification.; Palms--Identification.; Palms--Morphology.; Palms--Societies, etc.; Plants--Classification.; Plant morphology.; Plant anatomy.; Botanists.; Women scientists.; Women botanists.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Reprints, 1971-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Research, Apr 2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Research for Genera Palmarium from Natalie Uhl's desktop bookcase
- Research (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Coryphideae Final DNA
- Book and Article Information, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Corrections, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Comdat file for DNA (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Palm and Misc. Research (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Paytel paper for DNA (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Palm analysis (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Erwin Thesis (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Palm Development (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Misc., Dec 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Proofs of Color Covers, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Coryphoid Morphology (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Second Term- Oulline (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Bryales (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Botany 117 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Cytology- Botany 124 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Trees and Shrubs- Botany 117 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Let's Learn Spanish (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Botany 2E (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Botany 51 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Pondweed Classification (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Potamogeton (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Women in Science (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Taxonomy, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- NSF (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Anatomy Lab, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Palm- Misc. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Articles dipped from Science (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Botany- Course Outlines (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Plantations (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Pictures of Plants (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Grant, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Grant, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Grant Annual Reports (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Eames Bog (Box 2, Folder 23)
- New Projector Model, Jul 1978 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Grant, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Seminar (Moore), 1967 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- General (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Seminar (Bouks), Fall 1967 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- NSF (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Grant, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Palm Symposium, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Grant Symposium (Box 2, Folder 32)
- NCL Grant, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Revised Budget Grant, 1984-87 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Seminar, Spr 1968 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Abstract, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- NSF (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Tech, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Project (Box 2, Folder 39)
- History of Botany (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Botany Dept. History (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Straight Occupation, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Botany Dept. History (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Grant: Trees, etc. (Box 2, Folder 44)
- NSF Proposal: Systematic Biology, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Grant, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- NSF Proposal Reviews, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Grant, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Botany 115- Aquatic Plants (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Weeds (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Aquatic Plants (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Elatine (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Misc. Research and Class Notes (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1978-79 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1978-79 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Psychospermata, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- 1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Chazdon, Robin (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Grifo (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Cropper, S. Hagel (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Hodel (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Poh, Li Khang (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Mackel (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Freudenstein (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Geruais, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Grifo/Gunther (Box 3, Folder 22)
- McKamey (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Palm DNA (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Palm Fossil: Coconut (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Abstract, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Palm Guidebook, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Species Palmarum (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Attaela Crassispatha, Nov 1989 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Palm Guidebook (Box 3, Folder 30)
- New Guinea Specimens (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Carpoxylon (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Oraniopsis (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Monocot Phylogeny, Fall 1987 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Ceroxyloideae (Box 3, Folder 35)
  Floral Anatomy
- Incomplete Prophyll (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Caryota (Box 3, Folder 37)
- La Selva (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Data Sheets- Androecium (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Tables (Moore), 1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Androecium Coryphoid (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Androecium General (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Androecium Notes (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Seminar (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Seminar 1000 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Sindroa, Halmoorea (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Masoole (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Numerical Taxonomy Conference, Oct 1984 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Tomatoes, Walnut (Box 4, Folder 11)
- AIBS, 1978-79 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Coryphoideae (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Addressing Labels (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Technique Material to Clear, 1977-78 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Darkroom (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Welfia Development (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Floral Anatomy and Pollination (Box 4, Folder 18)
- AJB Plates, Misc. (Box 4, Folder 19)
- AJB Instructions (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Major Groups (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Paleobotany, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Ceroxylon (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Borassus (Box 4, Folder 24)
- EM-TEM (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Ceroxyloideae (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Areca (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Bactrius (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Alenga Tremella (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Bismarckia (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Borassoideae (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Bosch (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Butia (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Chamnedorea (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Iriarteoid Palms, Inflorescence Androccium (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Incomplete Prophylls (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Cyclonthaceae (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Corypha (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Corozo (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Geonoma (Box 4, Folder 40)
- Heterospathe (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Latonia (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Leopoldinie (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Lepidocaryoideae (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Metroxylon Vitiense (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Palandra- Vasculature (Box 4, Folder 46)
- Palandra, Phytelephas (Box 4, Folder 47)
- Paralinospadix (Box 4, Folder 48)
- Phytelephas (Box 4, Folder 49)
- Root (Box 4, Folder 50)
- Sabal (Box 4, Folder 51)
- Tareunia (Box 4, Folder 52)
- Thrinax (Box 4, Folder 53)
- Trachycarpus (Box 4, Folder 54)
- Species Concepts, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 55)
- Nypoideae (Box 4, Folder 56)
- Orbignya Speciosa (Box 4, Folder 57)
- Phoenix Reclinata (Box 4, Folder 58)
- Plectocomiopsis (Box 4, Folder 59)
- Podococcus (Box 4, Folder 60)
- Socratea (Box 4, Folder 61)
- Linospadix Monostachya (Box 4, Folder 62)
- Paralinospadix (Box 4, Folder 63)
- Linospadix Minor (Box 4, Folder 64)
- Wettinia (Box 4, Folder 65)
- Howeia (Box 4, Folder 66)
- Linodpadiceae (Box 4, Folder 67)
- Laccospadix (Box 4, Folder 68)
- Arecoideae (Box 4, Folder 69)
- Africa (Moore) (Box 4, Folder 70)
- Gynoecial Structure- Palms (Box 4, Folder 71)
- Trends- Leningrad Draft (Box 4, Folder 72)
- Phylogeny- Course Summary (Box 4, Folder 73)
- Stain Technology (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Stain Technology Notes (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Androecial Development (Box 5, Folder 3)
  First Complete Draft
- Stamen Development Reviews (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Centrifugal Stamens- Final (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Centrifugal Stamens- Copies and Reviews (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Centrifugal Development Final, Oct 1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- B.S. Manheim (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Centrifugal Stamens (AJB) (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Centrifugal Stamens (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Pollination Correspondence/Corrections (R. Schmidt) (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Pollination- Biotropica (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Pollination- Final (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Pollination- Penultimate (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Pollination First Draft (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Mayburretea, Liberbarley, Furtadoa (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Mayburretea, Hyophorbe (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Drawings and Manuscripts (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Acerrulus- Final (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Hyophorbe Leaf (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Hyophorbe (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Acenvulus- Final (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Hyophorbe- Flower (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Orchids- Eastern US (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Taxonomy Notes (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Nomenclature (Box 5, Folder 26)
- O.F. Cook (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Costa Rica, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Abstract- Congress, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Androecium AIBS, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Technique Androcciaum (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Phytelephantoids Leaf Anatomy (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Seedings (Sabal) (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Bougainvillea (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Biography (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Pogonotium (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Seedling Measurements and Data, 1977-78 (Box 5, Folder 37)
- Santa Barbara Botanic Garden (Box 5, Folder 38)
- Androecium, Gynoecium Photos (Box 5, Folder 39)
- Collections, 1963-64, 67 (Box 5, Folder 40)
- Collections, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 41)
- Collections, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 42)
- Research Club, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- Collections, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 44)
- Collections, 1974-78 (Box 5, Folder 45)
- Monocot Collection (Box 5, Folder 46)
- Development- Research Notes (Box 5, Folder 47)
- Congress, Seminars, Talks (Box 5, Folder 48)
- Genera Palmarum, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 49)
- Inflorescence (Box 5, Folder 50)
- CA, Apr 1977 (Box 5, Folder 51)
- Anatomy, Aug 1977 (Box 5, Folder 52)
- Colloquim- Floral Anatomy, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 53)
- Floral Anatomy of Palms \, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 54)
- Protection Seminar at McGill, Nov 1973 (Box 5, Folder 55)
- Seminar, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 56)
- Palm Lecture, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 57)
- Gynoecium AIBS and Seminar (Box 5, Folder 58)
- Raphia (Box 5, Folder 59)
- Palm Misc. (Box 5, Folder 60)
- Oncospermatae, Jul 1972 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Androecicim (Marion), 1978 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Androecicim-General, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Articles, Reviews, Class Materials, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Notes (Leningrad/Tulane) (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Families (Moore), 1969-1975 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Moore Tropical Families, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Seminar in Practical Botany, Fall 1972 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Conference, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Abstract, Seminars, Conference, 1976-78 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Palm Symposium (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Coevolution- Pollination, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Palm Seminar, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Pollination Seminar (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Keys to General Palms (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Lepid- Ultimate Units (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Inflorescence (Tucker) (Box 6, Folder 17)
- The Leaf (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Stems (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Leaves, Stems, Roots (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Malvales, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Arecoideae (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Caryotoideae (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Cocoideae (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Cocoideae (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Geonomeae (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Juania (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Juania (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Palm references (Box 6, Folder 29)
- Colyptrocolyx (Box 6, Folder 30)
- Xanthorrheaceae (Box 6, Folder 31)
- Chrysallidosperma (Box 6, Folder 32)
- Phoenicoideae (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Plant Seminar (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Series Completed XII, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Pittsburgh, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 36)
- Kew Symposium, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 37)
- Coryphoideae (Box 6, Folder 38)
- Systematics Agenda, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 39)
- Carpel- Reviewer's Copy (Box 6, Folder 40)
- SEM (Box 6, Folder 41)
- Hychosperms II- Corrected Copy (Box 6, Folder 42)
- Plant Collecting: Mexico (Box 6, Folder 44)
- Greenhouse, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 45)
- Cerox Data (Box 6, Folder 46)
- Clados Hennig Files (Box 6, Folder 47)
- Australia, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Correspondence- Fossils (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Nomenclature, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Cocosoids and Keys (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Hyophorbe (Harrison) (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Phytogeography (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Diagrams and Keys (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Chapter VI: Evolution and Relationships (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Photography (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Palm Program (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Anatomy Book (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Pollen Cytology (Box 7, Folder 12)
- NU Copies, GP Maps (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Speakers: Palm Symposium (Box 7, Folder 14)
- GP Comments (Box 7, Folder 15)
- GP Corrections (Box 7, Folder 16)
- M12 (Box 7, Folder 17)
- M13 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- M14 (Box 7, Folder 19)
- M15 (Box 7, Folder 20)
- M16 (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Misc. Prints (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Palm Literature List (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Palmetom and Final Correspondence (Tucker) (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Brazoria Palms (Box 7, Folder 25)
- Cocoeae (Box 7, Folder 26)
- Technique (Box 7, Folder 27)
- Unfinished Sketches and Touchups (Marion) (Box 7, Folder 28)
- Negatives for Master's Thesis Plates (Box 7, Folder 29)